<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bendeguz Seres</title>
    <link>http://bendeguz.xyz/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Bendeguz Seres</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 09:56:41 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://bendeguz.xyz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>UEFI and Secure Boot</title>
      <link>http://bendeguz.xyz/posts/uefi-and-secure-boot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 09:56:41 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://bendeguz.xyz/posts/uefi-and-secure-boot/</guid>
      <description>Not too long ago, I had to figure out how to boot into linux with secure boot enabled, without modifying the key database. As it turns out, this is not a trivial task, so I spent like half a day on a weekend, researching the topic, but I finally figured out a way to do it. I wrote this post in the hope that it could help others in similar situations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://bendeguz.xyz/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 20:59:22 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://bendeguz.xyz/about/</guid>
      <description>Hi! My name is Bendeguz. I’m a programmer living in Hungary. I’m currently working in the domain of IT Security.
My interests are mainly systems programming, embedded systems and computer science in general, mainly the theory of computation and programming languages.
I’m a firm believer of open source, the importance of decentralization, the UNIX philosophy and the hacker mindset. I think programming is one of the most creative and intellectually satisfying activities one can pursue.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python Environment</title>
      <link>http://bendeguz.xyz/posts/venv/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2020 22:09:41 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://bendeguz.xyz/posts/venv/</guid>
      <description>For making your life a lot easier while developing with python, it&amp;rsquo;s important that you know about the concept of virtual environments. With virtual environments, you won&amp;rsquo;t clutter your global environment, and you can even use different versions of specific packages.
Before we can discuss the topic of virtual environments, we have to know about package management in python.
PIP Pip stands for Pip Installs Packages (recursive acronyms are apparently very popular among tech people).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
